<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: government | E(X)PECTED P(A)YOFF]]></title>
  <link href="http://expectedpayoff.github.com/blog/categories/government/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://expectedpayoff.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-08T19:36:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://expectedpayoff.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Byron Gibson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Complex Costs of War]]></title>
    <link href="http://expectedpayoff.github.com/blog/2012/06/07/the-complex-costs-of-war/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T20:54:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://expectedpayoff.github.com/blog/2012/06/07/the-complex-costs-of-war</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://nancysherman.com/">Nancy Sherman</a> was the first Distinguished Chair in Ethics at the U.S. Naval Academy andis currently University Professor of Philosophy at Georgetown. <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/05/30/a-crack-in-the-stoic-armor/?src=me&amp;amp;ref=homepage%22">Her article</a> in the NY Times today discusses the subtle, complex, confusing costs to civilized people tasked to fight our modern wars.</p>

<p>"In the military, even those who have never laid eyes on a page of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epictetus">Epictetus</a>, still live as if they have. To suck it up is to move beyond grieving and keep fighting; it is to stare death down in a death-saturated place; it is to face one more deployment after two or three or four already. It is hard to imagine a popular philosophy better suited to deprivation and constant subjection to stressors [than <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism">Stoicism</a>].</p>

<p>And yet in the more than 30 interviews I conducted with soldiers who have returned from the long current wars, what I heard was the wish to let go of the Stoic armor. They wanted to feel and process the loss. They wanted to register the complex inner moral landscape of war by finding some measure of empathy with their own emotions."</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
