<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: election | E(X)PECTED P(A)YOFF]]></title>
  <link href="http://expectedpayoff.com/blog/categories/election/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://expectedpayoff.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-18T15:30:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://expectedpayoff.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Byron Gibson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Other Election 2012 Contest:  The Pollsters vs the Data Scientists vs the Political Markets]]></title>
    <link href="http://expectedpayoff.com/blog/2012/10/25/the-other-election-2012-contest-the-pollsters-vs-the-data-scientists-vs-the-political-markets/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T12:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://expectedpayoff.com/blog/2012/10/25/the-other-election-2012-contest-the-pollsters-vs-the-data-scientists-vs-the-political-markets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>"Election administrators go to bed at night and say, 'dear Lord, let it be a landslide.'"</em> -Trevor Potter, former commissioner and chairman of the FEC</p>

<p>Election 2012 is shaping up to be interesting for a variety of reasons, but not least because of two reasons involving forecasting:</p>

<ol>
<li>Sophisticated probabalistic electoral college forecast models first seen in the early-mid 2000s have had a few election cycles to mature and evolve.</li>
<li>This is the first <em>closely contested</em> presidential election since said techniques hit mainstream, and for the first time since then we're seeing disagreement among different forecasting methodologies.</li>
</ol>


<p>There are roughly three categories of data-driven, systematic forecasting methodologies:</p>

<ol>
<li>Traditional (but highly tuned) polls like <a href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/154559/US-Presidential-Election-Center.aspx?ref=interactive">Gallup</a>, <a href="http://pewresearch.org/topics/election'12/">Pew</a>, <a href="http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/political_updates/daily_presidential_tracking_poll">Rassmussen</a>, both of the national popular vote, state popular votes, and of registered and 'likely' voters.</li>
<li>Electoral college probability models/simulations run by data scientists like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nate_Silver">Nate Silver</a> (<a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com">fivethirtyeight.com</a>), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_S._Tanenbaum">Andrew Tannenbaum</a> (<a href="http://www.electoral-vote.com/">electoral-vote.com</a>), and <a href="https://twitter.com/DrewLinzer">Drew Linzer</a> (<a href="http://votamatic.org/">votamatic.com</a>), that incorporate polls, economic indicators, and other correlated variables to create a forecast model of the electoral college.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.macroeconomicwoes.com/uncategorized/the-policy-wonks-guide-to-the-presidential-betting-market.html">Political betting markets</a> like <a href="http://www.pinnaclesports.com/ContestCategory/Politics/Lines.aspx">Pinnacle Sports</a>, <a href="http://www.matchbook.com/matchbook/events/market/?category=138157">Matchbook</a>, <a href="http://www.intrade.com/v4/misc/scoreboard/">Intrade</a>.</li>
</ol>


<p>This is the first US presidential election since 2000 that is actually close and contested, and hence the first ever closely contested presidential election that features mature probability models of the electoral college - alongside tuned, tweaked, evolved and relatively sophisticated polls and betting markets - all attempting to divine the outcome.</p>

<p>One characteristic of this close election is that idiosyncracies, and perhaps flaws and biases, in these forecasting methods are more likely to be exposed under the higher general uncertainty than in the past two presidential election cycles.</p>

<p>Whereas uncontested or landslide elections tend to result in all the forecasting methods roughly agreeing with each other, close elections can result in disagreement among them - as is happening now - and hence a moment of truth: who is most accurate (or to put it in more scientific terms, who is <a href="http://serendip.brynmawr.edu/sci_cult/lesswrong/lesswrong/">less wrong</a>).</p>

<p>As of writing this, the major national polls generally show Romney eeking out a slight lead in the national popular vote, the electoral college models show a stubborn lead for Obama, and the betting markets generally favor Obama while trending Romney (with some <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/24/oct-23-the-virtues-and-vices-of-election-prediction-markets/">unusual activity</a> which could hurt their credibility even if they correctly predict the election).</p>

<p>So who is least wrong?  We'll know in about two weeks, and can look forward to plenty of postmortem analysies of the analysies afterwards.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
